Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the New American Movement PE.042
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the New American Movement
1972-1982
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.042
1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the New American Movement is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. NAM was a socialist-feminist organization, founded in 1972, with chapters across the country. The collection consists of printed matter ranging in date from 1972-1982. Contained within the files are fliers for marches, rallies, conferences and various events, as well as pamphlets, brochures and newsletters.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Historical/Biographical Note
The New American Movement (NAM), a self-identified "new type" of socialist organization, held its founding convention in Minneapolis, Minnesota in 1972. Established largely by veterans of the New Left, NAM wanted to move beyond the activism of the 1960s and rejected a vanguard approach to organizing. The group was opposed to the Vietnam War and called for the impeachment of President Richard M. Nixon. NAM's overarching goal was to create a democratic socialist society, characterized by racial, sexual and economic equality. In 1982, the organization joined with the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee to form the Democratic Socialists of America.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the New American Movement consists of a selection of printed material published by the organization at the national and chapter level ranging in date from 1972-1982. Contained within the collection are fliers and brochures for various NAM sponsored events, rallies, conferences and workshops. There are numerous pamphlets as well as serial publications including the national newsletter, Moving On. NAM was founded at a national convention held in Minneapolis, Minnesota in 1972; the collection contains publicity materials, political statements and agendas from the convention as well as from subsequent national conventions up until 1981. There are numerous pamphlets outlining the organizations' positions on various issues. In addition to the material put out by the organization at the national level, there are also files from NAM chapters, including from Radcliffe-Harvard, Austin, and from chapters in and around the Chicago and New York areas. In 1982, NAM merged with the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee to form the Democratic Socialists of America. The collection contains the material surrounding negotiations of the merger.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New American Movement Records (TAM 51)
Arrangement
The files are grouped in one series; folders are arranged alphabetically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
Newsletters.; News bulletins.; Clippings (information artifacts); Fliers (printed matter); Brochures.; Socialist feminism |z United States.; Socialism -- United States.; Socialism.; Pamphlets.; New American Movement (Organization)
- Amherst Chapter (MA), undated (Box 1)
- Ann Arbor Chapter (MI), 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- Anti-Racism Commission, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
- August 7 Network, 1980 (Box 1)
- Austin New American Movement (TX), undated (Box 1)
- Blazing Star (sll women's chapter), undated (Box 1)
- Brown University (Providence, RI), 1974-1975 (Box 1)
- Chapters (various), 1977-1982 (Box 1)
- Chicago Area Chapters, undated (Box 1)
- Circular Letters / Outreach, 1974-1982 (Box 1)
- Constitution, undated (Box 1)
- Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC), 1979-1982 (Box 1)
- East Bay Socialist School / East Bay Voice (Oakland, CA), 1975-1978 (Box 1)
- Energy Commission, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
- Fliers and Brochures, 1973-1982 (Box 1)
- Health Commission, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
- "Impeach Nixon" Campaign, 1973 (Box 1)
- Labor Commission, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
- Lesbian and Gay Liberation Task Force, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
- Middlesex New American Movement (MA), 1975, undated (Box 1)
- Minneapolis Chapter: Song Book, undated (Box 1)
- Moving On (newsletter), 1974-1976 (Box 1)
- National Convention, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
- National Convention, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
- National Council, 1980 (Box 1)
- National Interim Committee: Circular Letters, 1981 (Box 1)
- National Interim Committee: Meetings, 1981 (Box 1)
- National Interim Committee: Report to Membership, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
- New York City Area Chapters, 1975, undated (Box 1)
- Newsletters (various), 1973-1976, undated (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles About, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
- Northeast Region, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
- Northwest Region, undated (Box 1)
- Open Letters, Statements, Press Releases, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
- Pamphlets I, 1972-1981, undated (Box 1)
- Pamphlets II, 1972-1981, undated (Box 1)
- Pamphlets III, 1972-1981, undated (Box 1)
- Pamphlets IV, 1972-1981, undated (Box 1)
- Pamphlets V, 1972-1981, undated (Box 1)
- Pamphlets VI, 1972-1981, undated (Box 1)
- Pamphlets: "Where We Stand", 1976-1979 (Box 1)
- Pittsburgh Chapter (PA), 1976-1981 (Box 1)
- Political Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
- Radcliffe-Harvard New American Movement (MA), 1973-1975, undated (Box 1)
- Socialist Feminist Commission, 1981 (Box 1)
- Somerville New American Movement (MA), 1977 (Box 1)
- Speakers Bureau, undated (Box 1)